Finding Aid for James N. Morgan papers, 1939-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James N. Morgan papers 1939-2010 1947-1999
Morgan, James N.
0.5 linear feet
2014108 Aa 2
James N. Morgan was a professor of economics and researcher in the Institute for Social Research at the University of Michigan from 1949 to 1987. The collection ranges from 1939 to 2010 with the bulk being from 1947-1999. It includes biographical information, research, and writings that Morgan produced before, during, and after his time at the university.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by James Morgan (Donor No. 10921 ) in April 2013.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research without restriction.
James N. Morgan was born March 1, 1918, in Corydon, Indiana on his grandfather's farm. He had one brother, Burton. He also lived in Iowa City, Seattle, and Evanston with his mother. He earned his B.A. from Northwestern University in 1939, and his M.A. and Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1941 and 1947, respectively. He was appointed to an assistant professorship at Brown University in 1947, immediately after receiving his doctorate. Morgan began working at the University of Michigan in 1949 as a postdoctoral fellow in economics and he was appointed to assistant program director at the University's Survey Research Center in 1951. He was promoted to program director in 1956 and became a full professor of economics in 1958. He was awarded the Distinguished Faculty Award and was the first professor at the University of Michigan to receive the W.S. Woytinsky Lectureship Award in 1977. Upon retiring from the university in 1987, he was awarded the titles of Research Scientist Emeritus and Professor Emeritus of Economics. Over the course of almost 40 years at the University of Michigan, Morgan produced 30 books, 37 book chapters, and 25 journal articles. His research focused on consumer behavior, the distribution of income and wealth, economic survey methods, housing status, and more.
Morgan married Gladys Hassler in 1945 and had four children: Ken, Tim, John, and Janet. His wife passed away in 1996.
The James N. Morgan collection includes biographical information, research, and writings that Morgan produced before, during, and after his time at the university, spanning the years 1939 to 2010 with the bulk being from 1947-1999. The collection is organized in three series: Biographical Material, Correspondence, and Research.
Subjects:
Consumer behavior--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Morgan, James N., 1918-; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical Material
  The series Biography Material contains information about Morgan and photographs of himself, family, friends, and co-workers. Also included are various writings that Morgan produced, including those published in scholarly journals, newspaper articles, and personal musings and journals. These are all contained within one folder.
  - Biographical Material (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1939-2000 (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - "Can We Measure the Marginal Utility of Money?" 1945 (Box 1)
    - "The Burden of Important Duties: Comment," 1947 (Box 1)
    - "Milk Monopoly?" ca. 1947 (Box 1)
    - "Individual Savings in 1947 and 1948" 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Land Use in Central Boston," 1948 (Box 1)
    - "The Measurement of Gains and Losses," 1948 (Box 1)
    - "The New British Town and Country Planning Act," 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Providence Rhode Island," 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Bilateral Monopoly and the Competitive Output," 1949 (Box 1)
    - "A Note on the Justification for Price Discrimination," 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Survey Would Be Costly," 1965 (Box 1)
    - "An Open Letter to the Church on its Mission in the World Today," 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Letter to the Editor of Research News," 1988 (Box 1)
    - "A Meditation on Passing the Peace," 1988 (Box 1)
    - "Poor Would Feel Crunch of Higher State Sales Tax," 1988 (Box 1)
    - "Children Should Be Society's First Priority," 1989 (Box 1)
    - "Some Suggestions on Helping People with Alzheimer's," 1991 (Box 1)
    - "Recollections of Northwestern in the Late Thirties," 1992 (Box 1)
    - "Fiftieth Anniversary: A Half-Century Retrospective Account," 1995 (Box 1)
    - "An Account of Gladys' Travels," 1996 (Box 1)
    - "Some Reflections on the Life of Gladys Morgan," 1996 (Box 1)
    - "The Proper Economic Role of Government in a Free Society," 1998 (Box 1)
    - "Some Windmills at Which I Have Been Tilting," 1999 (Box 1)
    - "Article Perpetuates Notion that Social Security Can Fund Itself," 2008 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series is separated into two files. The first is a general file containing correspondence between Morgan and others within the department, as well as personal letters unrelated to academia. The second section is correspondence specifically regarding Study 721 and Study 745 which Morgan worked on at the Institute for Social Research at the University of Michigan.
  - General, 1955-1988 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Regarding Study 721 and 745, 1965-1967, 1969 (Box 1)
- Manuals
  The Manuals series contains two files. The first is the instruction manual for OSIRIS IV, a data analysis system used by the Institute for Social Research. The second file contains the first and second editions of the Statistical Analysis System (SAS) guide which replaced the OSIRIS system.
  - OSIRIS IV, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Statistical Analysis System (SAS) Guide for the OSIRIS User, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
- Research
  The Research series contains files on three specific studies that Morgan worked on. The first is Study 678 which looks at the income of various families across the country. The second, Study 721, is an examination of economic behavior. The final study, 745, is an analysis of working status as well as consumer finances. Study 745 is a combination of research from Study 721 and Study 741 (not included in this collection). The series also contains Morgan's data from the OSIRIS system, and a report on the limitations of survey data.
  - OSIRIS IV Data, 1978-1989 (Box 1)
  - Study 678: Low Income Study, Income and Welfare in the United States, 1960, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Study 721: Economic Behavior of Individuals, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Study 745: Study of Working and Planning and Survey of Consumer Finances (a combination of Study 721 and Study 741), 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Values and Limitations of Survey Saving Data, 1954 (Box 1)